Inventory of the Judith Ewell Papers, 1961-2008
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Inventory of the Judith Ewell Papers 1961-2008
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
UA 6.076
1.17
Ewell, Judith
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to all researchers
Acquisition Information
Acc. 2008.159 was received prior to 2007.
Biographical Information
Judith Ewell joined the Department of History at the College of William and Mary in 1971 and received her Ph.D. from the University of New Mexico in 1972. She served as Assistant Professor from 1971-1977; Associate Professor from 1977-1984; Professor from 1984-1988; and as the first Newton Family Professor from 1988 until her retirement in 2004. She was Graduate Director, and then Chair of the History Department from 1991-1998.
Ewell taught Latin American History at William and Mary and spent two years as a Fulbright Lecturer in Venezuela (1979-1980) and Ecuador (1994-1995). She was awarded the Thomas Jefferson Award in 1988 and the Commonwealth of Virginia's Outstanding Faculty Award in 1989.
In addition to her monographs (The Indictment of a Dictator, 1981; Venezuela: A Century of Change, 1984; Venezuela and the United States, 1996), Ewell published several textbooks and document readers, and served as editor for the journal The Americas: A Quarterly Review of Inter-American Cultural History. She also served as president of the Conference on Latin American History, and has been acknowledged for her dedicated professional service.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of two boxes of material created and collected by Judith Ewell, a professor of History at the College of William and Mary between 1971 and 2004. It includes papers Ewell wrote in college and graduate school; conference papers and programs; teaching materials from her year as a Fulbright Lecturer in Venezuela; correspondence about her publications; and contracts and other administrative material regarding her appointments at William and Mary.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Series 1: Education, Series 2: Professional Activities, Series 3: William and Mary Career
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Typescripts
Topical Terms:
College of William and Mary--Faculty and Staff; College of William and Mary. Dept. of History; College of William and Mary. Project Plus; State Council of Higher Education for Virginia; Women--Education--Virginia.; Women teachers
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Education 1961-1969
  This series consists of two folders of Ewell's undergraduate work from Duke Univeristy and graduate work at the Univeristy of New Mexico. It includes transcripts, test scores, and papers returned with grades and comments.
  - Undergraduate Work 1961-1969 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Graduate Work 1967-1969 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Professional Activities 1965-2008
  Ewell's research and teaching career focused on Latin America, and modern Venezuela in particular. This series contains her fellowships and awards; teaching materials (mostly in Spanish); conference programs and typescripts of papers delivered; published articles and reviews; correspondence with publishers; research materials; photographs; and one folder of personal correspondence. The two folders of undated photographs were received in separate envelopes.
  - AAUW Fellowship 1969 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Awards and Nominations 1974-1995 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Book Reviews of Ewell's Work 1982-2001 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Book Reviews Written by Ewell 1977-2000 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Clippings 1987-2008 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Conference on Latin American History 1992 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Conference Proceedings, Rocky Mountain Council on latin American Studies 1977 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Conference Proceedings, Universidad Metropolitana 1998 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Conference Programs and Talks 1976-1979 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Conference Programs and Talks 1980-1984 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Conference Programs and Talks 1987-1997 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Conference Programs and Talks 1998-2001, undated (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Correspondence with Publishers 1976-2000 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Draft, Historiography of Instituto de Investigaciones Historicas of the Faculdad de Humanidades y Education, Universidad Central de Venezuela undated (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Fulbright Lectureship In Venezuela, Application and Announcement 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Fulbright Lectureship In Venezuela, Lecture Outlines 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Fulbright Lectureship In Venezuela, Lectures 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Fulbright Lectureship In Venezuela, Teaching Materials 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Fulbright Lectureship In Venezuela, Teaching Materials 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - The Indictment of a Dictator 1973-1997 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Interview and Memorandum 1970 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Journal Articles 1977-1985 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Journal Articles 1986-1993 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Lecture Notes About Haiti undated (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Letters of Appreciation 1984-2000 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - NEH Fellowship 1984-1988 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - New University of Lisbon Intensive Course 1994 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Personal Correspondence 1973-1988 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Photograph, General Marcos Perez Jimenez and General Oscar Mazzei Sosa undated (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Photograph, Portrait of Judith Ewell undated (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Photographs, SCHEV 1989 (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Photographs undated (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Photographs undated (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Professional Correspondence 1985-2000 (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Research materials 1976, undated (Box-folder 1:37)
  - Research Materials, Women in Latin America undated (Box-folder 1:38)
  - Student List, Universidad Andina Simon Bolivar undated (Box-folder 1:39)
  - Studies in Third World Societies 1986 (Box-folder 1:40)
  - Teaching Contracts 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1:41)
  - Typescript, The Law of the Seas in the 1980s undated (Box-folder 1:42)
  - Venezuela and the United States 1996, undated (Box-folder 1:43)
  - Virginia Outstanding Educator Award 1989 (Box-folder 1:44)
- William and Mary Career 1976-2008
  This series contains several folders of material regarding Ewell's professional appointments and letters addressing salary inequity; reports on Latin American Studies and International Studies at William and Mary; and a folder of letters received from alumni in response to Ewell's article about Nicaragua, published in the Alumni Gazette
  - Address to President Sullivan 1992 (Box-folder 1:45)
  - Applications for Summer Research grants 1984-1986 (Box-folder 1:46)
  - Appointments, Contracts, and Lettters Regarding Salary 1977-1998 (Box-folder 1:47)
  - Correspondence Regarding Ewell's Article in the Alumni Gazette 1985 (Box-folder 1:48)
  - Department of History 1990-1992 (Box-folder 1:49)
  - Institute of Early American History and Culture 1991-1993 (Box-folder 1:50)
  - International Studies 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Latin American Studies 1990 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Photographs, Commencement 1988 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Professional Evaluations and Reports 1990-1997 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Project Plus 1976 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Promotion and Tenure Files 1977-1988 (Box-folder 2:6)